A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, Board of Trustees, Office of the Chairman, Office Files of Julius Stratton FA705
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, Board of Trustees, Office of the Chairman, Office Files of Julius Stratton
1960-1972
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation
FA705
4.8 Cubic Feet
Conditions Governing Access
Material is open for scholarly research, with prior archival review.
Material more than ten years old is open for scholarly research.
Select individual files are restricted, as noted. Permission to access these files must be obtained from the Ford Foundation before scholarly access is permitted.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Ford Foundation archive was deposited at RAC in 2011. Ford Foundation records, correspondence, reports, program files and officers papers were transferred to, and accessioned by, RAC beginning in 2011. Accessions continue as necessary.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Materials requiring specialized equipment for access (film, audio, video, slides) may be restricted from scholarly research dependent on availability of the applicable equipment.
Brittle or damaged items, or materials otherwise in need of preservation care, may be restricted from scholarly research at the discretion of the RAC Head of Archival Services/RAC Head of Reference.
Biographical / Historical
Julius A. Stratton (1901-1994) was an educator, academic administrator and foundation leader who served as Trustee of the Ford Foundation from 1955-1966, and as Chairman of the Board from 1966-1971. Stratton was President of the Massachusetts Institute of Technology (MIT) from 1959-1966, and also served that institution at various times as Provost, Vice President and Chancellor. Stratton held bachelor's and master's degrees from MIT (1932, 1925), and was awarded the degree of Doctor of Science in Mathematical Physics from the Eidgenossische Technische Hochschule of Zurich, Switzerland (1927). Stratton joined the MIT faculty in 1928, and taught in the electrical engineering and physics departments for twenty years. During World War II, Stratton served as Expert Consultant in the Office of the Secretary of War, and was awarded a Medal for Merit in 1946. He was a member of the National Academy of Sciences, the American Philosophical Society and the Council on Foreign Relations. Stratton retired from the Ford Foundation Board of Trustees in 1972.
Scope and Contents
The Office Files of Julius A. Stratton document Ford Foundation programs, administration and trustee concerns during the early years of McGeorge Bundy's Presidency. The files contain correspondence with grant seekers, grantees and Foundation staff, reports by consultants and grantees, staff memoranda, publications and news clippings. The collection measures 4 linear feet and is contained in 4 record cartons. The records document a wide range of Ford Foundation grant programs with an emphasis on fields of particular interest to Stratton, including education, science and environmental affairs.
Arrangement
The Office Files of Julius A. Stratton are arranged in a single alphabetical series.
Ford Foundation
- A, miscellaneous, 1965-1971 (Box 1 (SK 32778), Folder 1)
- Africa, 1966-1971 (Box 1 (SK 32778), Folder 2)
- American Association for the Advancement of Science, 1967-1968 (Box 1 (SK 32778), Folder 3)
- American Bar Association, 1968-1969 (Box 1 (SK 32778), Folder 4)
- American University of Beirut, 1966-1971 (Box 1 (SK 32778), Folder 5)
- Anshen, Ruth Nanda, 1967-1970 (Box 1 (SK 32778), Folder 6)
- Appleton Academy, 1970-1971 (Box 1 (SK 32778), Folder 7)
- Archives, 1967-1968 (Box 1 (SK 32778), Folder 8)
- Austria, 1966-1967 (Box 1 (SK 32778), Folder 9)
- B, miscellaneous, 1966-1971 (Box 1 (SK 32778), Folder 10)
- Bank Street College of Education, 1967-1970 (Box 1 (SK 32778), Folder 11)
- Baylor College of Medicine, 1971 (Box 1 (SK 32778), Folder 12)
- Bicknell, Eliot, 1970-1972 (Box 1 (SK 32778), Folder 13)
- Bicknell, William J., 1970 (Box 1 (SK 32778), Folder 14)
- Billings, Bruce H., 1969-1971 (Box 1 (SK 32778), Folder 15)
- Bliss, Robert L., 1969 (Box 1 (SK 32778), Folder 16)
- Brown, Harrison, 1968 (Box 1 (SK 32778), Folder 17)
- Burt, Wayne V., 1970 (Box 1 (SK 32778), Folder 18)
- C, miscellaneous, 1968-1971 (Box 1 (SK 32778), Folder 19)
- California Institute of Technology, 1966-1968 (Box 1 (SK 32778), Folder 20)
- Cambridge Civic Symphony Orchestra, 1964-1970 (Box 1 (SK 32778), Folder 21)
- Cambridge University, 1967 (Box 1 (SK 32778), Folder 22)
- Capitol East Foundation, 1970 (Box 1 (SK 32778), Folder 23)
- Carnes, Sheldon Y., 1969-1970 (Box 1 (SK 32778), Folder 24)
- Cedar Crest College, 1969 (Box 1 (SK 32778), Folder 25)
- Center for Information on America, 1968-1971 (Box 1 (SK 32778), Folder 26)
- Chestnut, Harold, 1969-1970 (Box 1 (SK 32778), Folder 27)
- Citizen Exchange Corps, 1970-1971 (Box 1 (SK 32778), Folder 28)
- Citizens' Crusade Against Poverty, 1966 (Box 1 (SK 32778), Folder 29)
- City College, 1970-1971 (Box 1 (SK 32778), Folder 30)
- Cold Spring Harbor Laboratory, 1966-1967 (Box 1 (SK 32778), Folder 31)
- Colombia, 1966-1968 (Box 1 (SK 32778), Folder 32)
- Columbia University, 1968 (Box 1 (SK 32778), Folder 33)
- Commission on Foundations and Private Philanthropy, 1968-1969 (Box 1 (SK 32778), Folder 34)
- Committee for Ethiopian Literacy, 1965-1968 (Box 1 (SK 32778), Folder 35)
- Council on Library Resources, 1960-1970 (Box 1 (SK 32778), Folder 36)
- D, miscellaneous, 1966-1971 (Box 1 (SK 32778), Folder 37)
- Dahl, Norman C., 1967-1971 (Box 1 (SK 32778), Folder 38)
- Daily and Sunday Mirror, 1971 (Box 1 (SK 32778), Folder 39)
- Dillon, Wilton S., 1968 (Box 1 (SK 32778), Folder 40)
- Dressner, Howard, 1967 (Box 1 (SK 32778), Folder 41)
- Dreyfuss, Henry, 1968-1970 (Box 1 (SK 32778), Folder 42)
- E, miscellaneous, 1967-1971 (Box 1 (SK 32778), Folder 43)
- Ecumenical Institute for Advanced Theological Study, 1969-1970 (Box 1 (SK 32778), Folder 44)
- Education – corporate support, 1967-1969 (Box 1 (SK 32778), Folder 45)
- Education – graduate, 1966-1967 (Box 1 (SK 32778), Folder 46)
- Education – institutional finance, 1967 (Box 1 (SK 32778), Folder 47)
- Education, Special Program in, 1966-1967 (Box 2 (SK 32779), Folder 1)
- Educational Facilities Laboratories, 1967-1969 (Box 2 (SK 32779), Folder 2)
- Ensminger, Douglas, 1970-1971 (Box 2 (SK 32779), Folder 3)
- Environmental research, 1969-1970 (Box 2 (SK 32779), Folder 4)
- Essex Institute, 1965-1968 (Box 2 (SK 32779), Folder 5)
- European Physical Society, 1969 (Box 2 (SK 32779), Folder 6)
- F, miscellaneous, 1966-1971 (Box 2 (SK 32779), Folder 7)
- Ford Motor Company dealers, 1969-1970 (Box 2 (SK 32779), Folder 8)
- Foundation Center, 1969-1970 (Box 2 (SK 32779), Folder 9)
- France, 1967-1971 (Box 2 (SK 32779), Folder 10)
- Fund for the City of New York, 1967-1968 (Box 2 (SK 32779), Folder 11)
- G, miscellaneous, 1966-1970 (Box 2 (SK 32779), Folder 12)
- Germany, 1967-1970 (Box 2 (SK 32779), Folder 13)
- Glennan, T. Keith, 1969-1970 (Box 2 (SK 32779), Folder 14)
- Goudsmit, S. A., 1968-1969 (Box 2 (SK 32779), Folder 15)
- H, miscellaneous, 1966-1971 (Box 2 (SK 32779), Folder 16)
- Hampshire College, 1966-1967 (Box 2 (SK 32779), Folder 17)
- Handler, Philip, 1966-1967 (Box 2 (SK 32779), Folder 18)
- Harris, Fred R., 1969 (Box 2 (SK 32779), Folder 19)
- Harvard University, 1966-1968 (Box 2 (SK 32779), Folder 20)
- Heald, Henry T., 1967 (Box 2 (SK 32779), Folder 21)
- Hoff, Philip H., 1966-1967 (Box 2 (SK 32779), Folder 22)
- Hoffman, Paul G., 1967-1968 (Box 2 (SK 32779), Folder 23)
- Hook, Sidney, 1968-1970 (Box 2 (SK 32779), Folder 24)
- Howe II, Harold, 1971 (Box 2 (SK 32779), Folder 25)
- I, miscellaneous, 1967-1971 (Box 2 (SK 32779), Folder 26)
- Independent Schools Art Instructors Association, 1969-1971 (Box 2 (SK 32779), Folder 27)
- India, 1966-1971 (Box 2 (SK 32779), Folder 28)
- Ingham, Kenneth R., 1970-1971 (Box 2 (SK 32779), Folder 29)
- Institute for Educational Development, 1966 (Box 2 (SK 32779), Folder 30)
- Institute for the Future, 1968-1970 (Box 2 (SK 32779), Folder 31)
- Institute for Science and Technology, 1966 (Box 2 (SK 32779), Folder 32)
- Institute of International Education, 1967-1971 (Box 2 (SK 32779), Folder 33)
- Instituto Brasileiro de Educacao, Ciencia e Cultura, 1965-1967 (Box 2 (SK 32779), Folder 34)
- Inter-American Committee, 1963 (Box 2 (SK 32779), Folder 35)
- International Botanical Congress, 1967 (Box 2 (SK 32779), Folder 36)
- International Centre for Theoretical Physics, 1968-1971 (Box 2 (SK 32779), Folder 37)
- International Division, 1967-1971 (Box 2 (SK 32779), Folder 38)
- International Institute for Medical Electronics and Biological Engineering, 1966-1967 (Box 2 (SK 32779), Folder 39)
- International Science Foundation, 1968-1971 (Box 2 (SK 32779), Folder 40)
- J, miscellaneous, 1967-1971 (Box 2 (SK 32779), Folder 41)
- Japan, 1967-1969 (Box 2 (SK 32779), Folder 42)
- Jenkins, T. H., 1967-1970 (Box 2 (SK 32779), Folder 43)
- K, miscellaneous, 1965-1971 (Box 2 (SK 32779), Folder 44)
- L, miscellaneous, 1967-1971 (Box 2 (SK 32779), Folder 45)
- Law of the sea, 1969-1970 (Box 2 (SK 32779), Folder 46)
- Louisiana State University, 1967-1971 (Box 2 (SK 32779), Folder 47)
- Lowry, W. McNeil, 1970 (Box 2 (SK 32779), Folder 48)
- M, miscellaneous, 1965-1971 (Box 3 (SK 32780), Folder 1)
- McDaniel, Joseph M., 1966-1967 (Box 3 (SK 32780), Folder 2)
- Makinac College, 1966-1969 (Box 3 (SK 32780), Folder 3)
- Mantell, Herman P., 1968-1969 (Box 3 (SK 32780), Folder 4)
- Marine Biological Laboratory – Woods Hole, 1968 (Box 3 (SK 32780), Folder 5)
- Massachusetts Historical Society, 1969-1970 (Box 3 (SK 32780), Folder 6)
- Massachusetts Institute of Technology, 1971 (Box 3 (SK 32780), Folder 7)
- Massachusetts Institute of Technology – Project Imtrex, 1966 (Box 3 (SK 32780), Folder 8)
- Meeting with Negro Leaders, 1966 (Box 3 (SK 32780), Folder 9)
- Mehra, Jagdish, 1971 (Box 3 (SK 32780), Folder 10)
- Museum of Science, 1966-1971 (Box 3 (SK 32780), Folder 11)
- N, miscellaneous, 1964-1971 (Box 3 (SK 32780), Folder 12)
- National Academy of Sciences, 1966-1970 (Box 3 (SK 32780), Folder 13)
- National Affairs, 1967-1971 (Box 3 (SK 32780), Folder 14)
- National Council on Crime and Delinquency, 1967-1968 (Box 3 (SK 32780), Folder 15)
- National Farmworkers Service Center, Inc., 1971 (Box 3 (SK 32780), Folder 16)
- National Service Secretariat, 1966-1968 (Box 3 (SK 32780), Folder 17)
- New England Conservatory of Music, 1965-1971 (Box 3 (SK 32780), Folder 18)
- New York Public Library, 1965-1970 (Box 3 (SK 32780), Folder 19)
- New York University, 1969 (Box 3 (SK 32780), Folder 20)
- O, miscellaneous, 1965-1970 (Box 3 (SK 32780), Folder 21)
- Oregon Graduate Center, 1966-1968 (Box 3 (SK 32780), Folder 22)
- Overhead charges in grants, 1970 (Box 3 (SK 32780), Folder 23)
- Oxford University, 1967-1971 (Box 3 (SK 32780), Folder 24)
- P, miscellaneous, 1966-1971 (Box 3 (SK 32780), Folder 25)
- Pay as You Earn Program, 1970-1971 (Box 3 (SK 32780), Folder 26)
- Pinck, Dan C., 1967-1970 (Box 3 (SK 32780), Folder 27)
- Polytechnic Institute of Brooklyn, 1966-1970 (Box 3 (SK 32780), Folder 28)
- Population, 1969-1971 (Box 3 (SK 32780), Folder 29)
- R, miscellaneous, 1966-1971 (Box 3 (SK 32780), Folder 30)
- Redwoods, 1966 (Box 3 (SK 32780), Folder 31)
- Regional Plan Association, 1967-1969 (Box 3 (SK 32780), Folder 32)
- Rockefeller, Laurence S., 1967 (Box 3 (SK 32780), Folder 33)
- Rogers, Frederick Rand, 1969-1970 (Box 3 (SK 32780), Folder 34)
- Ross, John, 1970-1971 (Box 3 (SK 32780), Folder 35)
- S, miscellaneous, 1965-1971 (Box 3 (SK 32780), Folder 36)
- Salk Institute for Biological Studies, 1963-1967 (Box 3 (SK 32780), Folder 37)
- Science and Technology, 1966-1969 (Box 3 (SK 32780), Folder 38)
- Seattle Historical Society, 1968 (Box 4 (SK 32781), Folder 1)
- Sex Information and Education Council of the U.S., 1969 (Box 4 (SK 32781), Folder 2)
- Singapore, 1969 (Box 4 (SK 32781), Folder 3)
- Singer, F. Fred, 1969 (Box 4 (SK 32781), Folder 4)
- Slater, J.E., 1967 (Box 4 (SK 32781), Folder 5)
- Southwest Center for Advanced Studies, 1966-1968 (Box 4 (SK 32781), Folder 6)
- Stanford Research Institute, 1970 (Box 4 (SK 32781), Folder 7)
- State University of New York (SUNY), 1968 (Box 4 (SK 32781), Folder 8)
- Steinbomer, Dorothy H., 1971 (Box 4 (SK 32781), Folder 9)
- Stone, Marshall H., 1968-1970 (Box 4 (SK 32781), Folder 10)
- Swiss Society of Sciences in USA, 1968-1969 (Box 4 (SK 32781), Folder 11)
- T, miscellaneous, 1967-1971 (Box 4 (SK 32781), Folder 12)
- Technical University of Berlin, 1962-1971 (Box 4 (SK 32781), Folder 13)
- Telescopes, 1966-1968 (Box 4 (SK 32781), Folder 14)
- Television, 1966-1970 (Box 4 (SK 32781), Folder 15)
- Travel and Study Awards, 1967-1971 (Box 4 (SK 32781), Folder 16)
- Trottenberg, Arthur D., 1969 (Box 4 (SK 32781), Folder 17)
- Tufts University, 1967-1968 (Box 4 (SK 32781), Folder 18)
- U, miscellaneous, 1966-1971 (Box 4 (SK 32781), Folder 19)
- United Nations – Advisory Committee on the Application of Science and Technology to Development (Box 4 (SK 32781), Folder 20)
- United Nations School, 1967-1968 (Box 4 (SK 32781), Folder 21)
- United State Congress – Patman, Wright, 1967-1968 (Box 4 (SK 32781), Folder 22)
- University of California Los Angeles (UCLA), 1966-1967 (Box 4 (SK 32781), Folder 23)
- University of Chicago, 1965-1968 (Box 4 (SK 32781), Folder 24)
- University of Hawaii, 1968 (Box 4 (SK 32781), Folder 25)
- University of Notre Dame, 1965-1967 (Box 4 (SK 32781), Folder 26)
- University of Oklahoma, 1967-1968 (Box 4 (SK 32781), Folder 27)
- University of Rhode Island, 1970-1971 (Box 4 (SK 32781), Folder 28)
- University of Southern California, 1969-1971 (Box 4 (SK 32781), Folder 29-32)
- University of Washington, 1966-1967 (Box 4 (SK 32781), Folder 33)
- V, miscellaneous, 1966-1971 (Box 4 (SK 32781), Folder 34)
- Vassar College, 1966-1970 (Box 4 (SK 32781), Folder 35)
- W, miscellaneous, 1967-1971 (Box 4 (SK 32781), Folder 36)
- Ward, F. Champion, 1966-1970 (Box 4 (SK 32781), Folder 37)
- Washington State Research Council, 1970 (Box 4 (SK 32781), Folder 38)
- Wheaton College, 1970 (Box 4 (SK 32781), Folder 39)
- Woodrow Wilson International Center for Scholars, 1971 (Box 4 (SK 32781), Folder 40)
- Woodrow Wilson National Fellowship Foundation, 1968 (Box 4 (SK 32781), Folder 41)
- Woods Hole Oceanographic Institution, 1967-1971 (Box 4 (SK 32781), Folder 42)
- World Health Organization, 1970 (Box 4 (SK 32781), Folder 43)
- Y, miscellaneous, 1967-1970 (Box 4 (SK 32781), Folder 44)
- Yale University, 1967 (Box 4 (SK 32781), Folder 45)
- Yanakieva, Nelly, 1968-1969 (Box 4 (SK 32781), Folder 46)
- Z, miscellaneous, 1966-1971 (Box 4 (SK 32781), Folder 47)